<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[The maid is the best that lies alone.]</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1675</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 5 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 1 1-bit group-IV TIFF page image.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A51293</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M264A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R221457</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99832763</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99832763</idno>
            <idno type="VID">37237</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A51293)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 37237)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1782:2)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>[The maid is the best that lies alone.]</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>1 sheet ([1] p.) : ill. (woodcuts)  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for J. Williamson in Canon street and at the Bible on London-Bridgee,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1675]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Verse - "You young maids that would live chary,".</note>
                  <note>Title from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Date of publication from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Imprint on p.[2] reads: Printed for R.H. &amp; J Williamson in Cannon street and at the Bible on London Bridge.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect. Filmed copy trimmed deleting title.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Ballads, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2007-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-02</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Rekeyed and resubmitted</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <body>
               <div type="ballad">
                  <pb facs="tcp:37237:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <!-- PDF PAGE 6 -->
                  <argument>
                     <l>
                        <hi>The Maids Chaſtity that is troubled in mind,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Againſt young-Mens inconſtancy, who proveth unkind:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>She gives warning to all Maidens that are in the Row,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>To take heed of falſe Young Men whereſoere they go.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </argument>
                  <opener>To a pleaſant new Tune.</opener>
                  <p>
                     <figure/>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <figure/>
                  </p>
                  <lg>
                     <l>YOu young maids that would live chary,</l>
                     <l>And live ſingle and not marry,</l>
                     <l>Nor contract your ſelves to none,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>For the Maid is the beſt that lies alone.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Cupid, Cupid,</hi> thou haſt done me wrong,</l>
                     <l>I have been thy ſervant now too long;</l>
                     <l>My heart was never free from care,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Since I was intangled in thy ſnare.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>In thy ſnare I have been fettered,</l>
                     <l>And often have my buſineſſe letted,</l>
                     <l>In following after <hi>Venus</hi> train</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>But the Maid is the beſt that lies alone.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Young men they will cog and lye,</l>
                     <l>Maidens they may weep &amp; cry</l>
                     <l>Truth &amp; Conſcience they uſe none,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>But the Maid is the beſt that lies alone.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>In this breaſt a heart I bear,</l>
                     <l>Tis none of mine I wiſh it were</l>
                     <l>Once it was mine, if I could have kept it,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>But now where it is, 'tis not reſpected.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Now I hope to have my heart again,</l>
                     <l>And keep it faſt from <hi>Venus</hi> Chain,</l>
                     <l>Lock it in this Breaſt of my own</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>But the Maid is the beſt that lies alone.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>VVhen I have gain'd it ſafe agen</l>
                     <l>Then I am free from all young men,</l>
                     <l>And never like to make this moan,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>But live a ſingle Maid alone.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Love is a torment who can abide it,</l>
                     <l>VVho better knows then them that has try'd</l>
                     <l>I count her but for a mad woman ſtill,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>That ſeeks to humor a young mans will.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <pb facs="tcp:37237:1"/>
                  <!-- PDF PAGE 6 -->
                  <p>
                     <figure/>
                  </p>
                  <lg>
                     <l>YOung men they be much blinded,</l>
                     <l>Only to know a maidensmind</l>
                     <l>Maids do not believe them if they ſwear</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Leaſt after they leave you in a ſnare.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>But try their hearts if that you can</l>
                     <l>Before that you love any man:</l>
                     <l>Love is fond &amp; fickle ſtill</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Then do not humor a young mans will.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>If a Lover be humored in his condition,</l>
                     <l>Then he doth plead with a ſtrong commiſſion</l>
                     <l>To get his intention if he can</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>The maid is the beſt that lies alone.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>For in lying alone ther's no harm taken,</l>
                     <l>And being of an unconſtant Love forſaken,</l>
                     <l>Its better then Gold or Silver ſtore,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>If that ſhe doth never ſee him more.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>A maid that lives in an honeſt carriage</l>
                     <l>Muſt be careful in her marriage</l>
                     <l>Young men are ſo deceitful grown,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>The Maid is the beſt that lies alone.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>True Lovers Knot may ſoon be ty'd,</l>
                     <l>And a maid too ſoon may be made a Bride,</l>
                     <l>That's not all in concluſion ſhown</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>But the Maid is the beſt that lies alone.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>There is many things for to conſider</l>
                     <l>If a man &amp; a woman go together:</l>
                     <l>If Love be wanting between them twain</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>She had better ſtill to lye alone.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>VVhen they come to a maid a wooing</l>
                     <l>They make no conſcience of their doing</l>
                     <l>But uſe all the deceit they can</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>But the Maid is the beſt that lies alone.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>There are falſe young men in my mind</l>
                     <l>Some proves croſs, &amp; ſome proves kind</l>
                     <l>I will not condemn them all for one</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>The Maids are beſt that lye alone.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Therefore I adviſe you conſider my Song</l>
                     <l>I write to maids, I'le do them no wrong</l>
                     <l>And ſtill I do tell you every one</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>The Maid is the beſt that lies alone.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
            </body>
            <back>
               <div type="colophon">
                  <p>
                     <hi>Printed for <hi>R. H.</hi> &amp; <hi>J Williamſon</hi> in <hi>Cannon ſtreet</hi> and at the <hi>Bible</hi> on <hi>London-Bridge.</hi>
                     </hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </back>
         </text>
      </group>
   </text>
</TEI>
